CONTACT INFORMATION Rm 614, Kelvin Building University of Glasgow Glasgow, G12 8QQ United Kingdom Work: +44 (0)14133 08855 Web: www.pauljwright.co.uk Email: paul.wright@glasgow.ac.uk Publication List: SAO/NASA ADS

RESEARCH SUMMARY My research interests are in solar and stellar physics, and my Ph.D. research has concentrated on one of the unsolved problems in Heliophysics – the coronal heating problem. During my Ph.D. I have gained expertise in numerous time-series analysis techniques and methods for recovering the differential emission measure (an ill-posed inverse problem) from a wide range of spectroscopic and narrowband data. I am also a member of the *NuSTAR* Heliophysics working group and I led the analysis of the first solar flare observed by the *NuSTAR* hard X-ray *astrophysics* imaging spectrometer. I have also developed a stellar flare detection algorithm based on the observations obtained by the *Kepler* space telescope to determine the superflare rate of the Sun.

EDUCATION

University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK

2014 - present

Ph.D. Solar Physics

Thesis Topic: *The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings* Advisers: Dr Iain G. Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

University of Southampton, Southampton, UK

2010 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

First-class honours (1:1)

Adviser: Professor Malcolm Coe

Harvard University/Harvard-Smithsonian CfA, Cambridge, MA, USA

2013 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

Thesis Topic: *The Superflare Rates of Solar-Like Stars* Advisers: Dr Steven H. Saar, Dr Jeremy J. Drake

CURRENT
ACADEMIC
APPOINTMENTS

Researcher, NASA Frontier Development Lab (FDL)

2018 – present

SETI Institute/NASA Ames Research Center, Mountain View, CA

Project: Predicting Solar Spectral Irradiance from SDO/AIA Observations

- An 8-week applied Artificial Intelligence accelerator established to tackle knowledge gaps useful to NASA's science and exploration goals, and humanity.
- Implemented Deep Learning algorithms (Convolutional Neural Networks; CNNs) such as U-Net, AlexNet and ResNet to predict disk-integrated Solar Spectral Irradiance (SSI) observed by SDO/EVE (MEGS-A) from high-resolution SDO/AIA images which share a common latent space.
- Predicted MEGS-A SSI with average relative discrepancies of less than 3% using a Residual Neural Network (ResNet) augmented with a Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP).
- Used a 1x1 CNN (equivalent to an MLP) to improve the computational speed for differential emission measure (DEM) inversion. Further improvement to the resulting DEMs were obtained by training a CNN to correct the DEMs to minimise the residual between observed and synthesized SSI.
- Received the NASA Frontier Development Lab "Contribution to Science" award.

Affiliate Staff Member, University of Glasgow

2017 – present

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

• Using the EBTEL hydrodynamics code to model light curves from coronal loops. The parameter space of these simulations will be constrained by observations obtained during the *NuSTAR* heliophysics campaign, and these simulations will be used to test a variety of analysis techniques.

PREVIOUS
ACADEMIC
APPOINTMENTS

Post-Graduate Research Assistant, University of Glasgow

2014 - 2017

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

Project: The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings

- Analysed observations of the Sun with *NuSTAR*, a telescope not designed for heliophysics. These observations are the most sensitive of their kind and have resulted in numerous, wide-ranging, highly-collaborative peer-reviewed publications.
- Analysed 20 million non-flaring coronal time-series in pursuit of signatures of the coronal heating mechanism. Techniques included time-lag analysis (cross-correlation), Fourier analysis, wavelet analysis, and local intermittency measure (LIM).
- Studied the temperature distribution of the solar atmosphere through the recovery of an ill-posed inverse problem (the differential emission measure, DEM) using techniques such as Tikhonov regularisation, Markov-chain Monte Carlo, Spline fitting, and Sparse Inversion (by Basis Pursuit).
- The press-release image produced from the *NuSTAR* observations obtained for Wright *et al.* 2017 was published by numerous news outlets and is one of the five iconic images from *NuSTAR*'s first five years in space.

Primary Collaborators: *Dr Iain Hannah*, *Dr Alexander MacKinnon*, *Dr Hugh Hudson*, *Dr Paulo Simões*

Visiting Researcher, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC)

2016

Heliophysics Science Division

• Explored the possibility of implementing DEM maps in the Helioviewer project, and their usefulness as an input for various established analysis techniques.

Collaborators: Dr Nicholeen Viall, Dr Jack Ireland

Research Scholar, Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA) Solar and Stellar X-ray Group

2013 - 2014

- Designed and implemented a sophisticated stellar flare detection routine for long-cadence (30 mins) *Kepler* data obtained from a proprietary set of spectroscopically verified solar-type stars in three open clusters.
- A preliminary report on this work had coverage by Science and the Smithsonian Magazine.

Collaborators: Dr Steven Saar, Dr Søren Meibom, Dr Jeremy Drake, Dr José D. do Nascimento Jr, Dr Vinay Kashyap

Summer Research Intern, University of Southampton

2013

Astronomy Group

• Investigated the presence of double blue straggler sequences in globular clusters using Hubble Space Telescope (ACS, WFPC2) data.

Collaborators: Dr Andrea Dieball

REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Marsh, A. J., Smith, D. M., Glesener, L. et al 2017. First NuSTAR Limits on Quiet Sun Hard X-Ray Transient Events, ApJ, 849, 131
- [2] Wang, J., Simões, P. J. A., Jeffrey, N. L. S. et al 2017. Observations of Reconnection Flows in a Flare on The Solar Disk, ApJL, 847, L1
- [3] **Wright, P. J.**, Hannah, I. G., Grefenstette, B. W., et al 2017. Microflare Heating of a Solar Active Region Observed with NuSTAR, Hinode/XRT, and SDO/AIA, ApJ, 844, 132
- [4] Kuhar, M., Krucker, S., Hannah, I. G., et al 2017. Evidence of Significant Energy Input in the Late Phase of a Solar Flare from NuSTAR X-ray Observations, ApJ, 835, 6

FIRST AUTHOR PUBLICATIONS IN PREPARATION (WORKING TITLES)	[5] Wright, P. J., Galvez, R., et al 2019. DeepEM: A Deep Learning Approach Inversion	to DEM	
	 [6] Wright, P. J., MacKinnon, A., Hannah, I. G., and Simões, P. J. A. 2019. Local Intermittency Measure: The Application to Active Region Light Curves [7] Wright, P. J., Hannah, I. G., Viall, N. M., et al 2019. The Thermal Time Evolution of Active Regions Determined by SDO/AIA 		
	[9] Wright, P. J. , Saar, S. H., Meibom, S., et al 2019. An Extension of The Age-De Superflare Rates to F- and K-Type Dwarfs	ependent	
	Conferences,	Invited Oral Presentations	
WORKSHOPS, & SCHOOLS	ISSI Team Meeting: Coronal Nanoflares, Bern, CH	2018	
	ISSI Team Meeting: Coronal Nanoflares, Bern, CH	2016	
	Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA, USA	2014	
	Oral/e-Poster Presentations		
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII, Palermo, Sicily, IT	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Hinode 10, Nagoya, JP	2016	
	National Astronomy Meeting 2016, Nottingham, UK	2016	
	Hinode 9, Belfast, UK	2015	
	Glasgow-Cambridge Flare Workshop, Glasgow, UK	2015	
	Poster Presentations		
	European Solar Physics Meeting (ESPM), Budapest, HU	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VII, Cambridge, UK	2015	
	National Astronomy Meeting (NAM) 2015, Llandudno, UK	2015	
	223rd AAS Meeting, National Harbor, MD, USA	2014	
	Schools Attended		
	CESRA Radio Summer School 2015, Glasgow, UK	2015	
	STFC Advanced Summer School in Solar Physics, Dundee, UK	2014	
	Additional Conferences/Workshops Attended		
	NuSTAR Heliophysics Workshop (remote participation), Berkeley, CA, USA	2017	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2015	
	Royal Astronomical Society Discussion Meeting: Results from IRIS, London, UK	2015	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2014	
	1st Space Glasgow Research Conference, Glasgow, UK	2014	
AWARDS AND	University of Classey		
AWARDS AND GRANTS TOTAL: £7000	University of Glasgow NASA Frontier Development Lab, Contribution to Science Award	2018	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (AAS/SPD) Student Poster Award	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (AAS/SPD) Studentship Award	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII Travel Award	2017	
	National Astronomical Observatory of Japan Travel Award	2016	
	Hinode 9 Travel Award	2015	
	European Space Agency/Cambridge Philosophical Society Travel Award	2015	

AWARDS AND GRANTS (CONT.)	University of Southampton Research Scholarship Summer Studentship Grant	2013 2013
TEACHING	Coursera Inc. "Data Scientists Toolbox" Community Mentor An invited mentor of a course in the Data Science specialisation offered by University.	2017 – present by Johns Hopkins
	University of Glasgow Astronomy 1 Tutorial Demonstrator Supervised students, and marked first-year astronomy problem sets. Astronomy 3/4 (Honours) Laboratory Demonstrator Demonstrated, supervised, and marked a number of final-year research topics such as asteroid light curves, and solar limb darkening. Physics Pre-University Summer School Taught at a pre-university school for students entering the first year education.	2015
Memberships	NuSTAR Heliophysics Working Group, Member International Space Science Institute (ISSI), Young Scientist Member Member of Paola Testa's ISSI Team: New Diagnostics of Particle Accelerational Nanoflares from Chromospheric Observations and Modelling Royal Astronomical Society, RAS Fellow	2015 – present 2015 – present leration in Solar 2014 – present
COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT	Nature Communications, Reviewer Glasgow Astronomy & Astrophysics Group Meeting, Organiser CESRA Radio Summer School, Volunteer Organiser	2017 – present 2017 2015
SCIENTIFIC OUTREACH	Glasgow Science Centre, Demonstrator British Science Week, Demonstrator Institute of Physics: Women and Girls in Science, Demonstrator Scottish Television (STV), Guest Presenter World Wide Telescope, Ambassador BBC Stargazing Live, Demonstrator So'ton Astrodome, Demonstrator BBC Bang Goes The Theory Roadshow, Demonstrator	2016 2016 2016 2015 2013 – 2014 2013 2012 2012
	UK Solar Physics (UKSP) Nuggets , concise, easy-to-read science articles 84. The first <i>NuSTAR</i> microflare	2017
	Hinode/XRT Picture of the Week (XPOW) The First Microflare Observations with <i>Hinode/XRT & NuSTAR</i>	2017
PERSONAL PROJECTS	ColourBlind, A repository for colour-blind-friendly colour tables.	

Professional

Coursera, Inc. (MOOC Platform)

DEVELOPMENT

Using Coursera.org, a massive open online course (MOOC) platform, to take specialisations (a series of related courses plus a final capstone project) offered by accredited universities to further develop skills and understanding in a wide range of topics.

Data Science, Johns Hopkins University

2017 – present

Nine-course (plus capstone) introduction to data science.

Mastering Software Development in R, Johns Hopkins University

2018 – present

Four-course (plus capstone) specialisation providing rigorous training in R.

TECHNICAL SKILLS:

Computing: IDL (5+ years), Python (2+ years), PyTorch, R, Bash, LaTeX, PyCharm, IRAF, git (GitHub, Gitlab), Microsoft Office, Adobe Creative Cloud, Linux/Unix, Mac OSX, Microsoft Windows

General: Data Analysis, Data Visualisation, Interdisciplinary Collaboration, Public Speaking, Teaching, Writing (Technical & Lay)